<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.3">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-02-11T18:54:17-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed/index.xml</id><title type="html">Kausar’s Blog</title><subtitle>Welcome to my blog! I like writing about technology, fitness, philosophy, history and just about anything I find interesting. I&apos;m fascinated by Artificial Intelligence and where it can lead our civilization. I hope to be part of this revolution, contributing in my own little way.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Habit Tracking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/11/habit-tracking/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Habit Tracking" /><published>2024-02-11T15:15:16-06:00</published><updated>2024-02-11T15:15:16-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/02/11/habit-tracking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/11/habit-tracking/">&lt;p&gt;We all want to look good, be healthy, lead meaningful lives, be… happy, or some variant of that word. Why is it that only a handful of us ever reach that destination? We live in a world that’s never been as technologically advanced and globally connected. Why is that so many of us feel more detached and lost in our lives? In this blog post, I delve into these questions, trying to unravel what might be the real cause of our suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;a-culture-of-excess&quot;&gt;A Culture of Excess&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Living in Chicago, and possibly one of the most well-developed cities in the world, I can attest to the fact that I have access to all the material comforts that an individual may desire. Supplied with a regular source of income, there are plenty of food options, great nightlife, and a diverse demographic. Looking outside-in, this seems like paradise, but it’s more of a double-edged sword than you might think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you have all these creature comforts, there’s a greater possibility of getting… &lt;em&gt;soft&lt;/em&gt;. You rarely seek new challenges, blindly do what you’re told, and chase a high, hedonistically following whatever pleasure you find in the moment – be it food, relationships, drugs, etc. Sooner or later, you begin to feel trapped. Since you only live from one high to the next, you begin to lose touch with your life. You wonder why you’re alive in the first place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s a scary place, I know. Much of modern life is predicated not on what we can acquire, but more around what we must avoid. In an individualistic society such as ours, it is imperative we develop mastery over our mind, building greater discipline and intention in our daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;discipline--freedom&quot;&gt;Discipline = Freedom&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is something I heard Jocko Willink once say and I couldn’t agree more. Graduating from university 2 years prior and living alone for the first time, I felt quite isolated. A university curriculum is quite rigid and there’s a sense of certainty that comes with living like that. My work life is completely different, especially the consulting job I’m in currently. You get moved around from one client to another, from one team to another, from one type of work to another, and you soon begin to wonder what the overarching theme of all this really is. What am I working towards?  What do I have to show for my effort? Is this what I’ve become, living off one paycheck to the next?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This feeling of meaninglessness continued to haunt me during my first 6 months on the job. But then things started getting better, and I wondered why. It came down to routine – and the daily habits I set for myself every day. A pivotal change I made was when I started writing in the 5-minute journal. I would start my day listing the 3 things I was grateful for, the 3 things that would make my day great, and 1 daily affirmation. I would end the day with the 3 highlights of my day and a sentence describing what I learned that day. That simple, but it made a huge difference.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For one, recurrent patterns that made me unhappy began surfacing in my writing. Too much caffeine, less sleep, poor diet, missed workouts – these were some of the common traps I fell into that degraded the quality of my day. When your flaws start becoming apparent to you, you begin to make corrections. I replaced these bad habits with good ones – working out daily, reading, honing my technology skills, practicing the piano and meditating. By writing it in my journal in the morning, I was held accountable for meeting this promise. Very soon, the quality of my life dramatically improved. Fundamentally, I think we all want to feel like we’re getting better at something. To evolve into more of who we are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;habit-tracking&quot;&gt;Habit Tracking&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“We don’t rise to the level of our expectations; we fall to the level of our training.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Archilochus&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I gamified this whole process, using an app called Habit. By logging the habits I complete in a day, I have quantitative proof that I am who I say I am. Triathlete, technologist, pianist, meditator – these are all identities I own because each day is an opportunity to cast a vote towards being the kind of person I would like to be. I’ve been using this app for over a year now, and I would like to now show you the progress I’ve been enabled to make with this consistent approach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/pics/habit-pillars.png&quot; alt=&quot;Habit infographic&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;learning&quot;&gt;Learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In July 2022, I had no idea what cloud computing really entailed. As of writing this in February 2024, I’ve earned 7+ cloud certifications, enrolled in Georgia Tech’s OMSCS program, and have plans to enroll in their on-campus machine learning PhD program. How did I do it? The answer, and it sounds obvious: I showed up every day and learned a little bit, incrementally inching towards the goal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of my motivation around getting proficient with cloud technologies was more work-related. The consulting firm I work at emphasizes that its employees use their free time studying for certifications and taking these IT exams. When I wasn’t staffed or had some spare time on my hands, that’s exactly what I did. Memorizing theoretical concepts in a rote fashion only got me so far though. What made the difference in my learning was using the cloud platform and applying what I learned. I would take a lot of practice exams, make mistakes, and learn from them. I would engage in hands-on labs, where I interacted with the cloud console in an interactive fashion, learning at a far higher rate. A bit of a flex, but I’m including the certifications I earned below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* AWS Certified Solutions Architect – Associate (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt;)
* Machine Learning Specialization (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt;)
* Mathematics for Machine Learning and Data Science (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt;)
* FinOps Certified Practitioner (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt;)
* AWS Certified Cloud Practitioner (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt;)
* Google Cloud Digital Leader (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt;)
* Microsoft Azure Fundamentals (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt;)
* Microsoft 365 Fundamentals (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;badge&lt;/a&gt;)
* &lt;em&gt;…and more!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I learned a lot in the process, but I felt something missing. There was a practical dimension that I hadn’t experienced. Just having the credential didn’t prove that you could do the job. I internalized this concern and worked on my first cloud project – the AWS Resume Challenge by Forrest Brazeal. It gave me a solid understanding of how to go about setting up a website frontend (link) and backend (link), and how to connect the 2 with an API. Incidentally, the visit count at the bottom of the home page was the key outcome of this project. I experienced an immense sense of pride upon completing that project. It made me realize that I love programming and building things. Honing this skill became my utmost priority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s when I came across the Georgia Tech OMSCS program – a fully online master’s program that would be offered at a fraction of the cost of an on-campus degree. Sign me in! So far, the courses I’ve taken have been fascinating and have kept me intellectually stimulated. I found myself spending more time on my homework assignments than my day job. The former felt far more exciting. That’s when I decided that it was time to go back to school in a full-time capacity. I would like to try my hand in machine learning research and build mastery within that subject area. A rigorous apprenticeship under a master in that field would be the best use of my time. That’s why I have set my sights on earning a PhD in the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The point of this whole story is for you to realize that if I can make it this far (and I still have a long way to go), then you can too! It all comes down to the work you’re willing to put in and how often you’re willing to show up.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;fitness&quot;&gt;Fitness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This has been the game changer in my life. If you looked at my pictures from 3 years ago, you would barely recognize me. In fact, let me include a before-after picture below:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/pics/before-after.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;A before-after picture&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I simply did not like the way I looked for the longest time. There was a sense of shame I felt that was eating into me. I had to take matters into my own hands, or I would have to silently suffer like this for all my life. That’s when I signed up for a gym membership at Anytime Fitness, Champaign IL on May 7th, 2021. I still remember the date because, from that day forward, my life would never be the same. Since writing this, I have gained considerable muscle mass, lifted more weight than I ever thought imaginable, learned to swim in the open water, completed 4 triathlons, become an active member of the CrossFit community, and I am only getting started.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The journey of a thousand miles begins with a single step. That first step involved overcoming inertia and showing up for my first personal training session, uncertain about what to expect. I remember paying around $500 for an 8-class package – a lot of money for a college student to spend. My friends (at the time) laughed at my decision, but I figured I would stick to my guns. Those $500 turned out to me the wisest investment I’ve ever made in myself. My coach taught me everything I needed to know about weight training and how to best use my time in the gym. He gave me nutrition advice, especially around protein intake. Within 4 months, I made incredible progress. My body had grown much stronger, and I discovered a newfound confidence I never felt before. I was hooked and each day offered an opportunity for me to get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Besides the sessions with my trainer, I mostly preferred to workout alone. And I made quite a bit of progress that way. But after about a year and a half, I got bored. The coaches I was training with weren’t making me uncomfortable and helping me push my limits. I needed a new challenge. That’s when I discovered the Chicago Triathlon Club, a community of triathletes that meet 4 days a week working on the different disciplines involved in a typical race – swimming, cycling, and running. The group dynamic was an absolute game changer. I ended up pushing far harder, worked more diligently, and always went the extra mile. After an incredible season, I was recommended to try CrossFit at Defined Training, Chicago. The community aspect is even more strongly emphasized here, and the coaches know you by name. It really does make a huge difference and makes you feel like you are part of a tribe. To build long-lasting habits, being around a like-minded group of individuals has accelerated my progress.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;piano&quot;&gt;Piano&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is the hobby I am most proud of. I played the piano for a brief period in high school but gave up after a few months. I regretted that decision, but realized it wasn’t too late. My piano teacher, Ela Kriss, in Lakeview, Chicago has been instrumental in my success. I show up for her lessons weekly and practice daily on my keyboard. Deliberate practice over sustained periods of time paid off in a major way. I can now play for small audiences and occasionally get an applause! It’s crazy to see that kind of progress in my 2.5 years, but it is possible. Including a few of my piano performances below in case you don’t believe me:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;* Plaisir d’amour by Jean-Paul-Égide Martini (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;)
* The Entertainer by Scott Joplin (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;)
* Rigoletto: La donna è mobile by Luciano Pavarotti (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;)
* Light &amp;amp; Blue by William A. Palmer (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;)
* On Top of Old Smokey by William A. Palmer (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;)
* O Sole Mio by Luciano Pavarotti (&lt;a href=&quot;&quot;&gt;video&lt;/a&gt;)
* &lt;em&gt;…and hopefully many more!&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;None of this has come easy, but I find playing music incredibly therapeutic. There are things I can’t communicate through words that I can only express through music. I really wonder why it is that certain classical pieces move us do deeply. The relationship between music and the mind is something I would love to explore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of habit-building, I have noticed that the minimum effective dose for building skills with the piano is practicing regularly for approximately 20-30 minutes. That’s it. And if done daily (which is the key ingredient), success will materialize. Playing in front of others has made the biggest difference in terms of my development as a pianist. Your priority shifts from “getting your reps in” to “making each rep count”. You really start to listen to yourself and the sound you’re producing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;meditation&quot;&gt;Meditation&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This involves sitting for 30 minutes daily meditating. I started off using the Waking Up app by Sam Harris for guided instruction. The instruction bit makes a big difference, as it brings you back to the practice of observing your breath if your mind wanders for too long. Doing this for just under 2 years, I’ve noticed how much calmer I’ve become. It’s given me a lot of clarity around the things that matter most to me in life. Fun fact: I completed a 10-day Vipassana meditation retreat during Thanksgiving in 2023. I’ll write a separate blog post about my experience!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;reading&quot;&gt;Reading&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t know if anything more can be said about the benefits of reading, but this undoubtedly expands my horizons. I learn about a diverse range of topics, develop the ability to focus over long stretches of time, enhance my vocabulary, and gain inspiration around how I can be a better writer. The only piece of advice I can give to anyone who wants to build a habit in this area is: read anything you like, and if you get bored, move onto the next book. Feel no obligation to complete it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;In Emerson: Mind on Fire, Robert Richardson writes that Ralph Waldo Emerson read “like a hawk sliding on the wind over a marsh, alert for what he could use.” Emerson read to “nourish and to stimulate his own thought.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Reading like a bird of prey - Austin Kleon&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;pitfalls&quot;&gt;Pitfalls&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Switching gears, I’d like to now talk about some of the common pitfalls on the road to building long-lasting habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;distractions&quot;&gt;Distractions&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;TV, social media, YouTube, etc. There’s no dearth of opportunities to distract yourself. What works for me is distancing myself from these conveniences as much as possible. It does not imply that I’m a Luddite; instead, it’s about developing a healthy relationship with technology. I keep my phone in another part of my apartment when I’m working, delete all social media apps (except WhatsApp), grayscale my phone, and keep my phone on airplane mode when I’m not checking it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ability to focus over extended durations of time on what could potentially be our life’s task is a critical skill. Our phones have the potential to ruin this treasure. I’ll expand on this sometime in the future. Reading Cal Newport’s works has greatly influenced my thinking on this subject.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;loneliness&quot;&gt;Loneliness&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of my work is solitary in nature. Nobody’s doing the work for you. It’s you versus you. It’s natural to feel lonely at time; I know I do. But over time, I’ve begun to enjoy my own company. As I’ve accomplished more, witnessing positive transformations over time, my relationship with myself has changed. I am my best friend and the greatest ally I have. Meditating and journaling have helped me tremendously to avoid sinking into depressive episodes. Going out for a walk, getting some sunlight, eating well, working out, sleeping well… these are the basics. I’ve started to take full responsibility for my own happiness; nobody else has the power to control that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;doubt&quot;&gt;Doubt&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where am I headed? Is any of this going to work out? Will I be a success? It’s not about the destination, it’s about the journey. That’s what I keep reminding myself of. The purpose of all this work is your own development. Whether you attain some desired goal is entirely out of your control and quite frankly not the point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;“Just as a well-filled day brings blessed sleep, so a well-employed life brings blessed death.”&lt;/p&gt;

  &lt;p&gt;Leonardo Da Vinci&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;h4 id=&quot;burnout&quot;&gt;Burnout&lt;/h4&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When you’re pushing yourself every day, it’s bound to feel at times like you’re running out of gas. And it’s something I experience as well, so reading about my experience may miss the target. When I feel overwhelmed, I focus on what’s essential, rather than checking all the boxes on my to-do list. The 5-minute journal has helped a lot in this regard, as it asks you to narrow down the 3 things that would make your day great. That daily sense of accomplishment makes a huge difference in staying consistent with the work you put in, maximizing one’s longevity in what they do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wrote this post as a reminder to myself, on what has worked for me, and how I choose to live my life. Developing routines and habits is at the crux of what we do as humans. The quality of our days ultimately defines the quality of our lives.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="habits" /><category term="self-help" /><category term="discipline" /><summary type="html">Building robust systems for physical, mental &amp; spiritual flourishing</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/pics/wanderer_painting.webp" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/pics/wanderer_painting.webp" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Morning Pages</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/04/morning-pages/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Morning Pages" /><published>2024-02-04T15:15:16-06:00</published><updated>2024-02-04T15:15:16-06:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/02/04/morning-pages</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/02/04/morning-pages/">&lt;h2 id=&quot;motivation&quot;&gt;Motivation&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Work in progress. I will write about why I started morning pages in the first place and what I hoped to gain from it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;daily-practice&quot;&gt;Daily practice&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How it actually shaped up, how it’s benefitted me.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;realizations&quot;&gt;Realizations&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Summarize the high-level takeaways from your writing and the direction it’s given you in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;serving-it-raw&quot;&gt;Serving it raw&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Providing an introduction to this section. Broke them down into themes and contexts so the reader can skim around as they see fit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;talking-about-graduate-school-the-omscs-program-building-mastery&quot;&gt;Talking about graduate school, the OMSCS program, building mastery&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: Talk about what was on your mind prior to writing this portion. Assume the reader doesn’t know you.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I keep hearing this voice in my head that says I should go back to school, pursue a graduate degree. I wonder where this feeling comes from. I think I’ve always wanted to learn more, and be more effective with the work I put out into the world. To put these thoughts into action, I’m starting off with the Georgia Tech degree that would MAX take me 3 years (till 2026). My OPT may expire by then, and I may be in a different geography, getting accustomed to some big change in my life. I may even harness the GTech momentum and pursue a more specialized Master’s or Engineering + MBA degree (although I’m weary of more school). No matter what, I need it to be HARD. No cutting corners. These experiences must be able to provide me with a tangible skill set. I want to build the mental rigor to be able to look at this wonderful world of ours in novel, useful ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will not compromise my fitness during these pursuits. I know my family will support me if I ever need financial help. They’re onboard with the direction I would like to take my life in.
The KBAI class at Georgia Tech is not easy, but I do believe I have what it takes to succeed. I would like to get an A in this class, so that my academic advisor is convinced that I have what it takes to succeed in the on-campus version of the program. Gaining the opportunity to study at this prestigious university will be a huge privilege. I want my life to be an adventure, one that I am proud of living. Studying AI and implementing my own models that could one day have a real-world impact would enable me to work towards something that’s larger than myself. I don’t necessarily want to be remembered or celebrated. What is most important is that I live a life that is aligned with my own values, and I can look back knowing I did my best.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal for these next ~3 months will be to pour my heart and soul into this class. I really do wish to move to Atlanta next year and begin my training as an AI programmer. I hope to do myself proud, challenging my intellectual limits and marveling at the work I produce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently came across the audiobook of ‘Mastery’ - Robert Greene’s book. The part that stood out to me was when he spoke about the 3 steps within the apprenticeship phase: (1) deep observation - the passive mode, (2) skills acquisition - the practice mode, and (3) experimentation - the active mode.
With a mental skill like computer programming, it remains the case that I would learn best through practice and repetition - the natural learning process. Mindlessly consuming MOOCs and certifications will only lead to diminishing returns after a point. I’m quoting the book directly here - “We learn a foreign language by actually speaking it as much as possible, not by reading books and absorbing theories. The more we speak and practice, the more fluent we become.” That’s my intention with going back to graduate school, dedicating myself to the practice of programming, becoming a skilled AI engineer in the process. School will help focus me, narrowing my view on the one skill I can master, which will serve as a foundation for acquiring others. This will develop my concentration. Trying to multitask will be the death of the process. Learning new skills within computer science will involve tedium. I have experienced this on numerous occasions while trying to debug my programs. Rather than avoiding this inevitable tedium, I will rewire my mindset. I will accept and embrace this part of the journey, remain equanimous about it. The pain and boredom we experience in the initial stages of learning a skill toughens our minds, much like physical exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to adopt this philosophy in graduate school, and in my journey leading up to it as well. It’s the practitioners who eventually get ahead. The skills I acquire at Georgia Tech will open doors to new start-ups in the AI space, where I can take on the role of an engineer, a much more hands-on role than what I’m currently in. I know deep in my bones that this is the path I must take to eventually attain mastery within my field, contributing my own skills to the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A school like Georgia Tech brings its own set of ancillary benefits - prestige and alumni access. Such signaling would help me build a professional network. One’s impact in life is magnified with a well-curated team rallying along. Building relationships in the program overlaps with the first step of the apprenticeship phase - the passive mode. By quietly getting a lay of the land, I’ll be able to identify my own inclinations and strengths. I’ll also know who I’d like to partner with in the future. There will be considerable room for self-reflection during this part of the journey. Signaling can be compared to that initial pull of attraction we all feel when we see a good-looking person. But this attraction is only skin deep. What truly sticks is real skill - actual value that you can provide to an interaction. Enduring relationships are built around this fact - where energies match and both parties stand to gain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This takes me back to relationship-building. “How do I feel around this person?” is a valuable question to ask oneself. Instinct, gut feeling, intuition - these must never be ignored. The subconscious can reveal a lot more that the rational / logical mind can find hard to comprehend. There are limits to our own understanding. Much like how f(x) != x, there are gaps in our own reasoning processes we must reconcile with as we try to draw causal proofs. There’s a Mark Twain saying - “it’s not the things we don’t know that gets us in trouble, but the things we are damn sure of that just aren’t so.” Twain understood causal opacity better than most of us today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-meditation-and-the-realizations-ive-begun-to-have&quot;&gt;On meditation and the realizations I’ve begun to have&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since I started meditating last year, I began to realize how much calmer and intentional I felt about everything I did thereafter. In an environment where I am mostly by myself, it is important to stay level-headed and avoid spiraling out of control. There have been days where meditating has been difficult. My mind would be distracted by a constant stream of thought and it can be difficult to avoid engaging them. I think it’s a matter of practice. Upon meditating consistently, I have been able to deal with these sensations in a more equanimous manner. I’m less distracted and more at peace. I look forward to my daily meditation sessions. 20 minutes everyday is a worthwhile investment. I hope to go on a meditation retreat this year. I would like to experience what it would be like to remain in a meditative state for hours at a stretch. It’s fascinating to learn more about the nature of mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Funny how the pain in my knee was so pronounced at the start of the day, but subsided as time went by. Maybe it’s linked to blood circulation. After sitting cross-legged during my meditation, I noticed the pain subsided as I proceeded to get up. In terms of diagnosis and treatment, I want to test 3 broad areas: stretching and mobility, learning about good running form, and foam rolling as a habitual exercise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My eyes feel exhausted, quite fatigued. I think I’ll go to sleep early today. It felt good to do less today – go on a walk, meditate, read in silence – these are experiences I haven’t dialed into for a while. It gave me an opportunity to calm my mind and gain some perspective.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s so true that our interior experience of the world around us ultimately defines the quality of our lives. I will keep that in mind. Meditation has really helped me from that perspective. Becoming aware of my thoughts, emotions, state of mind, and not being identified with any of it, has granted me a great deal of psychological freedom. I seek to live this day in the best way possible, trying to realize the true nature of my mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A topic I’ve been meaning to write about, but haven’t quite gotten around is my 10-day Vipassana retreat during Thanksgiving week. Sitting in silence for that long provided me with 2 clear-cut truths: (1) I only love myself, and (2) I am 100% the cause behind my own misery. If we truly love ourselves, we must take full responsibility for our own happiness. The aim is to develop a certain degree of detachment from others – nothing they do/say can affect me in any way unless I let it. It’s only the most selfish person that can be the most virtuous. I would never want to hurt others because I know I would end up suffering more. That’s caused a great perspective shift within me. If someone is mean to me, I’m beginning to realize that that person is suffering, and projecting their own pain onto me. Nothing is really personal when you see it that way. The object of craving/aversion is only an illusion. It’s an individual’s inner impurities that prevent them from realizing their true nature. Even the act of craving/aversion is downright delusional. Every object/person you see around you is impermanent. Everything has a nature of arising and passing away. What’s the point of grasping at something that is so ephemeral? What are you running towards, and what are you running away from? The quote by Marcus Aurelius remains true – “you never step into the same river twice”. You change as a person, and so does the river. It’s all constantly evolving phenomena. It hurts to say this at times, but I sometimes look at my parents and realize… even they are temporary. Soon their time will also come and they will no longer be the same conscious entities they are now. Life is so precious, and also so fleeting. The only thing that matters is this present moment – that is all we really have. One can endlessly distract themselves with all kinds of worldly possessions but miss the real point of life - to live, now. That’s all one can do. To be fully alive. “The precious privilege of being alive, to see, to think, to enjoy, to love”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since the meditation retreat concluded, I have generally preferred to be in my own company and talk sparingly. A lot of what we say feels so banal and futile. Sometimes I feel we only talk to avoid tuning into the chatter within our own mind. Always say less than necessary. Beyond creating a level of mystique around the individual, it also demonstrates self-restraint. A person who talks less is more aware of their senses – taking in every percept more attentively. You let the world reveal itself to you, rather than blinding yourself with your own preconceived notions of how things should be. Nature is the ultimate judge. Time is what ultimately reveals what works within a complex system and what must be discarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Along these lines, even the act of speaking has appeared only recently in the context of humans being around in the world. There were pre-verbal societies, where reading one’s body language was enough to infer what the other being was trying to express. I’m quite sure this truth applies even today. Instead of taking someone’s words at face value, it might be worth dialing into their facial expressions instead. Those are far harder to fake. Our subconscious helps with this too. For example, despite noticing all the surface-level green flags in a potential partner, your gut/intuition says something entirely different, warning you regarding a potential threat. There are elements that your conscious mind is not able to detect. But the deeper parts of your brain (areas that have developed over a longer evolutionary period), can signal aspects that are harder for you to rationalize. These are the moments where I surrender, and accept the limitations of my own logical mind. Nature’s far smarter than me. She’s been around for longer, while I haven’t. I’d be a fool to ignore the gift provided to me over millennia of evolutionary cycles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The ideas expressed above are a mix of what I came across in a podcast with Robert Greene as well as Taleb’s Incerto series. There’s a dilemma I’m grappling with after having read their work. Greene speaks about writer’s block and how that really is a form of resistance one experiences before attempting a difficult task. I feel that way many times before I leave for a workout. There are times where I simply shut a part of my brain and head over for my workout anyway. Taleb, on the other hand, believes in surrendering to one’s own nature and not forcing anything. If you feel like writing, write. If you’d like to procrastinate instead, then feel free to do so. I may have misunderstood what the latter was trying to say. I, for one, see a lot of sense with what Greene has to say. A lot of good comes out of working against one’s own laziness, pushing past your pain threshold, and becoming more of who you are. I feel a deep sense of accomplishment by the end of my day when I string a set of hard tasks together. That may be what the deepest parts of our nature demand from us. To fight against stasis, complacency, and grow against all odds. Anything less and we’re not doing our lives any justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Seen this way, the end-goal / outcome of our actions seems trivial compared to the journey of self-discovery one undertakes daily. Alex Hormozi says this quite eloquently – that he’s happiest when he’s in pursuit of a particular goal. Achieving the goal is boring. The process is what’s fun. That’s what our days really comprise. As Hrithik Roshan says, “it’s never the end”. We’re always in the arena, each day is an opportunity for us to prove ourselves. The most profound thing one can do in their lives is to do their best at whatever their calling is. Nothing is as important as choosing to give your blood, sweat, tears… just about everything - to pursue your life’s task. There’s a deep sense of peace one can experience on the other side of this journey, if they know looking back that they gave it their best. That’s all you ever have to do. Virat Kohli once said this as well - that he doesn’t want to have the feeling when he retires that he didn’t give it everything on the pitch. David Goggins says this too. The one thing that continues to haunt him is if he gave every ounce of his energy into whatever it is he was pursuing. The 40% rule holds true – most of the time, we’re only limiting our potential to that small percentage. Arnold follows the same philosophy, that he doesn’t start counting his weight repetitions until they begin to hurt. There’s a bit of stoicism blended into the above mindset. What you’re essentially doing is segregating what’s in your control and what’s not. You’re not phased by what’s happening outside. The only validation you seek is internal. Any signs of success and failure in the external world begin to look like sides to the same coin. Much like craving and aversion. Running towards one and away from the other is madness, and can cause meaningless suffering.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking back at 2023, I can confidently say this was my best year so far. And I think the reason for it is the robust systems I built around me. The discipline I was able to harness to stick to my routine is what ultimately made all the difference. By remaining consistent with the process, I was able to see results I never dreamt would be possible. Not rushing the process, remaining patient, and letting things take their time have been the key ingredients behind my success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming out of the meditation retreat, there was a conversation I had with 2 of my peers that remains at the back of my mind. Our task at the retreat was to remain equanimous – to simply observe the sensations arising in one’s body, regardless of whether they felt pleasant or unpleasant. It was particularly difficult to endure those extended periods of bodily discomfort. Those were the times we really wanted to switch posture. The key learning our instructor wanted us to internalize was how ephemeral even the pain is – it’s all temporary, ‘anicca’. Pain can be a beautiful thing when seen through that perspective. When you push past your pain threshold while working out / studying, you are planting the seeds for further transformation. You are laying the groundwork for your destiny to actualize itself. To quit in the middle because the pain felt intolerable is doing a disservice to ourselves. That’s the mind game SEAL instructors play on aspiring soldiers during Hell Week. The pain can feel agonizing, hopeless even, and you don’t know if this will ever stop. The people who give in and quit, ringing the bell, may find immediate relief, but begin to regret throwing in the towel. Taking stock of one’s emotions and developing perspective on one’s pain in the heat of battle could possibly be the most valuable weapon one can have in life. Giving up is never an option you can be happy with. Rage, rage against the dying of light. By harnessing pain wisely, you can turn it into fuel. It all serves a purpose. There’s real gold to be found as you tread deep into your pain cave.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A related takeaway for me from that retreat was ‘upeksha’, or equanimity. Don’t chase any particular sensation. Surrender. Few phrases I heard Mr. S.N. Goenka repeat - ‘Accept the present moment just as it is, not as you would like it to be. Work diligently. Diligently, patiently, and persistently. Patiently and persistently. You are bound to be successful. Bound to be successful. If there is ever a time you get lost in thought, simply start again.’ I could see how well these mantras translate to our day-to-day lives. If you get lost, you can always begin again. Remain aware.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each day is an opportunity for me to chisel at this new self I’m trying to sculpt. I would like every minute to be targeted at this purpose. Anything that doesn’t serve that purpose must be discarded. I’ve been using meditation as a tool to untie the vicious, negative knots my mind gets trapped in. These are all impediments and distractions. They’re not real. I’m grateful to have found the Waking Up app and all of its incredible meditation sessions. This might sound too good to be true, but the impact of meditating consistently these past 10 months has been life altering. It’s made me relate to my experience as a human in an entirely different way. I have managed to attain a great degree of psychological freedom. I am a much calmer and peaceful individual. I am happy to be by myself, and really like the person I am. I’m so grateful to be living such an incredible life, doing the things I love. I really couldn’t be bothered by the outcome of my actions (higher pay, Ironman, PhD etc). I could be dead tomorrow and wouldn’t ever live to see these dreams come true. The only thing that matters is this present moment and whether I’m embracing my life and savoring it for all it has to offer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meditating over one’s death makes you realize that you really have nothing to lose. As Steve Jobs said in a Stanford commencement speech, you’re already naked. As John Maynard Keynes once said, “in the long run, we’ll all be dead”. That mere fact can provide a lot of clarity as to one’s mission in life. Everything someone says, thinks, or does is born out of that knowledge. Humata, Hukhta, Huvarshta - good thoughts, good words, good deeds. It’s a Parsi saying I once heard John Abraham mention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;developing-a-stoic-mindset&quot;&gt;Developing a stoic mindset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Writing this before going to bed today. It was the first day at work right after the week-long summer break. I spent half of the time networking with colleagues within my practice. I’ve been looking forward to getting involved with cloud engagements occurring at my company. Getting my name out there, helping them out, studying for certifications – these are productive ways to spend my time. No matter what happens in the future, at least I’ll be able to look back at this time and know deep down that I did what I could.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been feeling too great about my job. Market conditions have driven up inflation, which has led to clients avoiding engaging in large contracts with professional services firms like ours. The result is that the partners’ hands are tied in terms of the budgets they can allow for their teams. They staff fewer individuals. I’m still in the early stages of my career, and I haven’t yet built a strong skill base. That makes it harder to staff employees like me. There isn’t a compelling case for putting me on a project, besides me being a relatively cheap resource. It is a bit disheartening, but I also know how much of this is outside my control. I will keep networking and making every effort to help out where I can. I’ve thought about this multiple times. I’m ready to accept any outcome that emerges from this. Even if I’m laid off, I can quit knowing I did everything in my power to get involved with work within the firm, made an honest effort to follow my curiosities, and interacted and collaborated with my fellow colleagues to the best of my abilities. There will come a time when I am a highly sought after resource. I know this because of all the work I put in every single day, honing my skills. Getting AWS certified, learning more about cloud computing, pursuing the Georgia Tech degree, building a strong foundation in machine learning – I think all of this will compound towards some massive gains in the future. And, more than the goal, I find the work incredibly rewarding. I feel everyday is well spent when I learn something new. I’m embarking on a wonderful journey that can only lead to positive outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to write about the importance of giving one’s best, regardless of the outcome. When it comes to work, things are tough. Work isn’t available as much as before and it’s a struggle to stay billable. In such a situation, it is easy to get cynical and blame the company for not taking care of its employees’ development. However, feeling sorry for oneself and complaining does not do anyone any good. It’s a victim’s mindset, and it’s something I refuse to adopt. I choose to have the most positive attitude in this situation. I am networking quite actively every single day, in addition to helping out with pursuits and internal initiatives where I can. Something that I won’t compromise on is my learning, and how I prioritize upskilling. I’m really proud of the effort I put in to pass the AWS Solutions Architect Associate exam. It wasn’t easy, but that’s what made it so rewarding. I will continue with this trajectory, taking more certifications and giving my best at Georgia Tech. With this mindset of showing up everyday, networking, delivering high-quality work and learning, I know I can’t go wrong. The more love you put out into the world, the more you get back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m following a similar mindset with my triathlon training. I show up everyday, eager to put in the work. More than any particular result, I have thoroughly enjoyed the learning process. Getting better at swimming has been the most rewarding experience. Swimming 2.1 miles in Lake Michigan was incredibly empowering. The day I complete my first race swim is the day I will know that my fears were just that - fears. With enough patience and persistence, anything is possible. It really is the mindset I bring to this activity that will ultimately allow me to prevail. As I’ve begun to lead a more respectable life, I sense a growing positive energy within me. This aura will attract the best possible people into my life. My life is rewarding simply by virtue of how I choose to lead it. What is in my control, I will execute with the finest degree of precision. Anything outside the bounds of my direct influence is none of my concern. It’s a simple principle, but incredibly powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am so grateful for being in a place in my life where I can be happy, peaceful, and content with the fact that I can go out everyday with a passion for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently came across an interesting idea - being on an information diet. I think it’s quite pertinent for the times we live in. We’re deluged with noise across social media channels and various other apps. It’s up to us to take personal responsibility and recognize the ill effects of modern media if not kept in check. I’ve always preferred reading books, learning about a subject in depth, rather than remaining at a surface level by scouring 2 minute news bites / tweets. I enjoy watching Tim Ferriss and Lex Fridman podcasts for this very reason – they’re long-form and allow you to engage with the content in an in-depth fashion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to take a moment to address the injuries/pains that keep creeping up in different parts of my body during triathlon training. Going into the sport, I knew there were going to be issues. First with the left shoulder, then the left quad, now the right knee after today’s run… At some point, I need to realize that this is all part of the game. How I choose to respond to these occurrences is what will ultimately define the quality/nature of my experience. In terms of the right knee, my strategy is to inform Ryan at Athletico via email tomorrow. I’ll try to schedule a session for Monday. In case he’s unable to diagnose the issue, I will ask him if he could recommend a doctor to take a look at it. Who knows, this might be an occasion where I learn more about running technique and how best I can avoid injury.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;philosophical-rants&quot;&gt;Philosophical rants&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was listening to a talk on stoicism earlier in the morning, and one of the topics delved into our idea of happiness and how best we can go about achieving it. A lot of this can be explained by a gap we all perceive, between what we want and what we have. By bridging this gap, we tell ourselves we’ll finally be happy. We do this unknowingly, only to find out we’ve created another gap for ourselves after fulfilling our previous desires. This pattern can be likened to a hedonic treadmill, where we keep trying to fill a void with things, only to find ourselves craving for more. It’s also illuminating to think about our present selves. There was a time in the past where we wanted all the things we currently have, but we’ve conveniently forgotten about those days. The talk centered around the theme of gratitude, and how we must learn to want the things we currently have. It is the only way to escape the web of desires we trap ourselves in. I try to seek a sense of contentment in the daily activities I engage in. Whether that’s working out, reading, or learning a new skill – I’m trying to celebrate the present moment and remove myself from expecting any future reward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I am incredibly fortunate to be in the most prosperous nation on this planet, working in the technology space. I will soon be positioned to learn about concepts and exercise skills that could have an impact on many people. The fact that I’m earning well, living in a nice apartment, eating good food, engaging in hobbies I’m interested in, having the resources to learn about concepts I’m interested in - there are MILLIONS of people on this planet who would kill to be in my shoes. As I go about my life, I must continue to remind myself of this truth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I want to remain in this present moment, and celebrate the life I currently lead. I should seek to live everyday to its fullest. My purpose in life is to express myself to my greatest capability, leaving nothing on the table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over this past year, I have had the good fortune of realizing the kind of life I wish to be leading, and what I am unwilling to do and derive no joy from. That clarity has helped me make decisions that are based on sound principles and reasoning. Unlike many of my peers, I don’t feel the need to be pulled in multiple directions. I am content with my values and the path I’ve set for myself. It’s of least concern to me to think about what other people are doing and how they perceive me. Nothing will ever get in my way and I will make sure that I stay true to myself and my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I haven’t been speaking much to friends and family this week. Part of it may be due to how busy I keep myself over the week with my habits. It’s also worth noting that my parents prefer to call me at night (their morning). This is when I’m beginning to fall asleep and it’s best practice for me to turn off all digital devices and cut off all screens. I think it comes down to the choices we make and the tradeoffs we’d be okay living with. I believe we’re all here for a unique purpose. There will never be another individual with this unique strain of consciousness. Therefore, my likes, dislikes, opinions, choices, lifestyles - they’re all my own and I should not expect anyone to follow this path. I must know myself and be at peace knowing at my core that I am headed down the right path. This is exactly the person I was meant to be at this given moment. I really like this saying by Nietzche that you must “follow no one” and to “not try” by Bukowski. This means one should be their authentic self. Another saying by Nietzche that has really stuck with me over time is - “I see no greater purpose in life than to perish in attempting the great and impossible”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also want to take this opportunity to tell you directly that you have what it takes to thrive in the OMSCS program. I felt I was missing something through my time as an undergraduate, having not studied computer science and not becoming technical enough to solve hard challenges. That also hints at a few of my intellectual insecurities and how I’m unsure about being able to handle the OMSCS course load. But I’m here to tell you that you can do it. This may sound like a Hallmark postcard, but I really do mean it. You graduated with a degree in Industrial Engineering with a really high 3.79 GPA. You kept learning even after graduating, taking multiple cloud certifications and landing a respectable, technical role within the ICSR practice. Your time management skills have gotten really strong. You’ve been able to balance your fitness with work and additional hobbies in a sustainable way. There will be times when the courses get difficult. This is to be expected. But remember, you can do anything you set your mind to. Get a B, that’s fine. Take 1 class per semester, that’s fine too. But never, ever give up on your academic dreams. Always give your best. After my STEM OPT ends, I wish to go back to school, perhaps Georgia Tech, and continue my graduate studies. From that point on, I will either pursue a PhD or head to work in a more technical capacity, building products/systems that will amplify my impact in the AI space. There is a broader purpose here for you to stay true to. There will be people and events in your life that will try to get in the way of this dream. You must have the wherewithal and fortitude to not let it negatively impact you, but only make you stronger. Amor Fati.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m so proud of all the things you have been able to achieve. Know that you’re capable of great things. This is only the beginning. I have started to respect you more than ever. And you’ve done this through every action you’ve taken that’s led you on this positive, upward trajectory. Don’t worry, you’re on the right path. Keep going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of my favorite moments in life have been when I’ve been fully immersed in the present moment, being in a state of ‘flow’. I’d like to see my life as an ongoing adventure. The destination is unimportant, and, in fact, not even the point. We never really live to see the end anyway. It is this present moment that we really only have. I would like to remind myself of this truth every now and then, falling in love with every moment I experience. Savor my life. Who knows how long any of us have? If I don’t internalize this, I might end up worrying about every triviality – recognition, fame, adulation, praise, money, the next promotion. We chase these things ultimately realizing it’s not what we wanted in the first place. I don’t think what we truly want can be verbalized. It can’t be thought. It comes from being fully immersed with your life. The answer will present itself. But there will be no way you can verbalize / formalize / trap it on paper. The moment is fleeting, and each second gives us the opportunity to reconnect with our lives, to begin again.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At the risk of sounding esoteric, I want to switch gears and talk about how this is relevant to our own lives. Be it triathlon / CrossFit / graduate school / work / piano, there have been numerous occasions where I have just wanted to check a box and move on to the next thing. Replicate that same compulsion across the rest of your life, and imagine how drab, hollow and uninteresting your life would prove to be? Your whole life will become a culmination of simply checking boxes. No room remains to treasure your life. What then is the point of it all? What’s the endgame? I’d like to change course, and surrender to my present reality. Live it to the absolute fullest. Relish every element of it – the happiness, pain, sorrow, grief, depression, ecstasy, melancholy, gratitude, contentment, peace – they are all threads within this expansive fabric of life. They all add up to the whole. Embrace all of it. Amor Fati. It’s all necessary, and it’s in the here and now for a reason. The quality of your life will come down to the quality of your attention in every moment. It really is the most basic building block for living with love and intention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What would I change about my beliefs if I had the same experiences you did? It’s a line I came across in Morgan Housel’s book ‘Same as Ever’. Our paths in life are unique. We’ve all been exposed to a particular set of experiences that makes us believe the things we have in our minds. Tim Ferriss made this his billboard quote - “don’t be too sure of your own thoughts”. It’s a reminder for me to stay open-minded and remain aware of my own blind spots. It’s a great quality one can have to constantly refine one’s own world view. It’s a mark of a person who’s actively engaged with their lives. It’s true that nobody can really change my mind about anything, only I can do it for myself. No one else can walk the path for you. An idea tangentially related to this topic is around consciousness, and AI’s ability to extend this capability to extend it across beings. If I would like to viscerally experience your life, could there be a way for Brain-Computer Interfaces (BCIs) to enable us to do so? Neuralink and Musk have been working on this and I’d be curious to learn more. It may help us dig deeper into the nature of our own experience, understand the root of our own suffering, and work with it, rather than against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a world as dynamic as this, the only error one can make is to not take any risks. That’s what Sam Altman, co-founder of OpenAI, said in a Y-Combinator podcast. Machiavelli says this too - make mistakes of ambition, not mistakes of sloth. There’s no way one can avoid taking risks. The best thing you can do is to manage your downside, while remaining open to the possibility of convexity effects - a huge payoff that justifies all the small losses made along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s funny how envy works. People get jealous, not realizing they wouldn’t want 100% of anyone’s life. There’s a smarter subset of people who begin to use envy as fuel, as inspiration, instead of something to bicker about. The idea of a singular role model seems a little faulty as well. I would never want to wholly emulate anyone anyway. Instead, there are a selection of admirable qualities I’d like to imbibe from the various people I’ve come across, whether in reality or media. This is the better approach - take the orange, throw away the peel. Keep the gold, discard the rest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-following-a-north-star&quot;&gt;On following a north star&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Aside from the goal of passing, I think the Solutions Architect exam is quite interesting. It passes down some practical knowledge about how AWS operates, and how one can go about designing effective workloads in the cloud. It will reflect well on my knowledge and abilities when I pass the exam. It will help me differentiate myself in the workplace. I see this exam as a starting point.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The machine learning specialization at Georgia Tech will help even further. I’m currently reading this book called ‘Life 3.0’ that talks about AI and the role it will play in shaping human civilization in the following decades. To have a meaningful role to play in this saga, I believe it’s exceedingly important to begin investing in my knowledge and learning new skills. This process will be challenging (as it is now), but every piece of effort I make daily will inch me towards this vision I’ve created for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to preface all of this by saying I will only seek to do what I believe is in humanity’s best interest. There’s a lot of ongoing debate around AI safety, and I wish to be on the right side of this historical tipping point. I will work hard, gain rare and valuable skills, and make a positive impact on the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I don’t want to go down the rabbit hole of analyzing what positive/negative means in this context. However, superintelligent systems could pave the path towards humans leading more meaningful lives. How that happens is still up for debate. As I progress through my career, I wish to keep this north star in mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would not want to be an individual who’s chasing after the next promotion, or a larger paycheck. We’re all here for a reason, and I wish to utilize the limited time I have in a meaningful way.
Besides the learnings and readings I engage in, my life will turn out to be unique due to my other hobbies – like fitness and music. These are activities that will differentiate me as a human being, allowing me to have novel experiences and seeing the world in a unique way. This distinct worldview will enable me to provide my own special contribution to the world. I will be able to go through my life knowing that every day adds up to a full expression of my being. More than any worldly rewards like money/adulation, this internal barometer is what will ultimately define my satisfaction with life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Most men lead lives of quiet desperation, and go to the grave with that song still in their hearts” - Henry David Thoreau. This is a quote that bubbled up in my head yesterday. The words I’d like to harp on are “quiet desperation”. There’s a disturbance in the psyche that needs addressing. This ties in well with the north star document I created for myself as a compass to follow. “To be in harmony with myself and others”. It’s an antidote to the sense of ‘desperation’ one experiences in their life. It’s possible to overcome this nagging feeling. As long as we work towards actualizing our mental and physical potential, to realize our own greatness. To truly achieve a level of personal sovereignty, an inner peace that’s independent of what’s happening around me, to be in constant pursuit of the joy one can experience being fully human. These are weighty words, but I do think there’s some truth to this. There’s a degree of autonomy that’s born out of showing up everyday and doing one’s best within the constraints an individual finds themself in. Mind, body, and interpersonal relationships – these are the 3 pillars that support personal wellbeing. In my life, I try to stay intellectually stimulated with the work I do, books I read, certifications I study for, and degree I progress in. From the body perspective, I train hard - making sure the body is never disobedient to the mind, as Seneca points out. Taking care of my body and pushing my limits is the primary source of my day-to-day fulfillment. The relationship part is a work in progress. I have family and friends that are an integral part of my life. I value their presence in my life. At times, I falter with maintaining contact. It gets hard to do since we’re not physically proximate. On the other hand, to achieve a state of harmony in my interpersonal relationships, I’m being more intentional around the kinds of people I wish to surround myself with. Setting the right boundaries, defining the rules of engagement, forgiving quickly, choosing to not feel harmed and complicit in taking offense – this is how I plan on building my own inner citadel and remaining tranquil.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m beginning to realize the importance of setting a clear vision in one’s life and how to get there. Initially, my objective was to get to America, so I pushed myself to score well on the ACT, applied to a bunch of schools, and eventually landed a spot in the industrial and systems engineering department at UIUC. My next objective was to get a job, a prestigious one, and consulting seemed like a good pick. I networked, filled my resume with experiences, practiced for interviews, and eventually landed a position as a technology consultant at Ernst &amp;amp; Young (EY). What I’m realizing now is it might be time for a change. This time, I want to dream big. Be audacious. Be hungry. Be foolish. At this point, I’ve realized one thing. I have an intense hunger within me to prove myself. I work hard once the goal has been set. This time, I want to push the limits of what I think is possible. Something I could not have conceived of a few years back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m having visions that one day I’ll be leading my own company, a top-tier AI startup that delivers value to people around the world. The idea, product, and team will perfectly coalesce. To get closer to my goal, it will be best that I become a full-time student at Georgia Tech, immersing myself within the Atlanta community, pursuing cutting-edge research opportunities. I’d like to push the limits of my own intellectual capabilities, taking challenging classes like machine learning, deep learning, reinforcement learning, etc. Most importantly, this graduate degree will open doors for me, giving me the opportunity to get involved with a high-growth start-up and be part of building a great product. This experience will be worth its weight in gold. The objective this time isn’t to settle for a high-paying job. It may seem tempting, considering this is what most of your peers will do. But remember, there is a bigger game to play. We are on the precipice of an AI revolution and there’s a great deal of value that can be extracted. It’s in moments of disruption that incumbents fall and new companies take their place. This is your moment. Everything that has happened in your life thus far has been a training ground for this very moment. Do not let it pass you by. I’m glad I got the opportunity to work at EY this early in my career because it gave me direction, making me realize my own likes and dislikes. More than anything, I love having absolute ownership over the product I deliver. I take pride in the quality of my work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Arnold says, developing a clear vision is such a crucial part of the journey. Within technology, I will play the role of an AI leader, bringing to fruition a type of AI technology that is novel and valuable. I will be the one responsible for defining this new future. I will be the one creating this new world, a new culture, a new society. It will be my contributions that enable this. All the steps I take from now till this point will only serve to bring me closer to my goal. Within the field of fitness, I will be a top-rated Ironman athlete and an inspiration for all Indian and Asian men on what is truly possible. I will bring a unique voice to the world of fitness as I will be one of the only individuals who also has strong ties with the AI world. I will be able to use my cross-domain expertise to draw unique connections, taking the world of fitness to the next level, aided by AI. I will also be a great pianist/musician. The art I create, especially with the assistance of RNNs and other AI technology, will enable me to generate a prolific outpouring of content, differentiating me as a prodigious artist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;having-a-practitioners-mindset&quot;&gt;Having a practitioner’s mindset&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trial and error - the value of tinkering to get one’s desired results. I came across this idea from reading Taleb’s “Antifragile”. The book talks about the value of being a practitioner, an individual who has a net positive impact on the world. He contrasts this ideal with a theoretician, someone who is keen on giving advice without any skin in the game. I found this idea quite compelling. It’s the direction I’d like to take my life in. Instead of getting stuck giving empty advice or turning into a boring academic, I would find much more meaning building tools that are of value to the people around me. Programming is a skill I love improving upon. I enjoy the process of iterating on my work until I get it to a desired place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I would like to be an individual who is antifragile. That’s a person who grows regardless of the stressors they are exposed to. It’s linked to the idea of Amor Fati, a love of one’s fate. No matter what situation I find myself in, I will always use my circumstances as fuel – pushing me to further grow, and becoming the person I was always meant to be. Becoming who I am. Like Hydra, if life tried to cut one of my heads, two more would grow in its place. There’s wisdom in the saying that “the more you do, the more you can do”. It’s like building muscle. You can keep getting stronger as you begin breaking your own limits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I read a piece on nutrition by Peter Attia some time back. He spoke about nutrition’s black-box nature. We keep going around professing one diet after another, not knowing what works and what doesn’t. The topic’s complicated because one food can affect two people in entirely different ways. There’s so much we don’t understand about the interaction between food molecules and our own biochemistry. He points out that only one fundamental truth about nutrition is known – that energy input must match energy output as closely as possible to maintain equilibrium. The obesity issue in the world is linked to individuals ignoring this fact. We eat mindlessly without any care in the world regarding how much we’re expending. We live in a society filled with plentitude, and that has brought with it its own share of problems. I want to harp on the importance of sticking to the fundamentals of any particular field, like nutrition above. This must be done before venturing into overly complex terrain. The latter looks sophisticated, gives off an aura of intellectual superiority, but is most often than not a more illusion. By sticking to first principles, and building from there, one can never go wrong. This is related to a conversation I recently had with an entrepreneur in Silicon Valley. He spoke about the many talented engineers he’s interacted with over his three-decade long career. All of them had one thing in common – an appreciation for the fundamentals. The reason they stuck around in their jobs for so long was because everyday turned out to be an adventure for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Everyday was an opportunity for them to refine their own knowledge structures and continue building their skillset. This is how a practitioner’s mind works. An individual who is a perpetual wanderer - a flâneur - is always tinkering around with what they know, exploring new territory, and ultimately driving innovation and growth in the world. That’s the kind of person I’d like to be. I fear becoming a mere academic, who makes his money giving advice to people without any real ownership in the overall outcome. That’s cowardice. We are better at doing than understanding. The world is too complex and a lot of it beyond our rational comprehension. The best way we can move forward is to learn by doing. That’s why I find the field of computer science so exciting. I have an opportunity to write my own programs and build my own systems, directly serving society. Instead of theorizing endlessly, I get the chance to be a do-er, someone who creates instead of aimlessly talking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;racing-in-triathlons&quot;&gt;Racing in triathlons&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My first triathlon turned out to be kind of a disaster. June 11th, 2023 - That’s the day I competed at the Fox Lake Sprint Triathlon. These past 3 months, I’ve been training at the Chicago Athletic Clubs to get in shape for a triathlon. I’ve been waking up at 4:45 AM from Tuesday – Friday working on running, swimming, cycling and core workouts. I put in a lot of work and looked forward to seeing how I would fare at the race.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Events did not transpire as I hoped. As the race started, I began swimming in Nippersink lake. After a few strokes and meters later, I realized how choppy the water was. Open water swimming is a very different beast compared to swimming in a calm pool. Every time I looked up, the waves would keep crashing into my face. I began gagging as the water entered my mouth. I couldn’t breathe. I was panicking. People on the side passed me by. “Slow down your breathing”, “It’s going to be okay”, “You got this”, “Do you need help?” But I knew I couldn’t carry on. My lungs gave out and I had no energy left. I floated a bit, thinking I could conserve a bit of energy before carrying forward. But it was a hopeless situation. I decided to swim back to shore and took the DNF. I still went on to complete the bike and run because…why not? I gave it my best, and I failed. So what? I TRIED. And this is only the start. Today’s events made me realize where I stand in terms of my triathlon readiness. I will work my ass off to get better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of my most memorable moments was meeting the 80-year-old man who was also competing in the race. While making conversation, I flattered him a little saying I would like to be like him when I age. He looked at me seriously and showed me his hand. “Be careful what you wish for” He had four fingers.
The people in the race made the whole experience worthwhile. I am very grateful to Jack, a tri buddy, for offering me a ride. He was great company and I liked our conversations. The post-race brunch was a great opportunity to get plugged into the CAC community and interact with everyone. It makes these events a truly rewarding experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Coming out of Fox Lake, I vowed to take action. I signed up for private swimming lessons with Steve in addition to Monika’s group classes. The former would take place on Monday at 5:30 PM, and the latter would take place as usual at 6:00 AM. I began open water swimming at Ohio Street beach between the 11 AM and 7 PM time range. This accustomed me to wearing my tight wetsuit and the various factors I would have to consider while open water swimming. I signed up for another sprint triathlon in Wauconda, which will take place in July. This will be a good primer before the Chicago triathlon in August.
Fast forward to July 23, 2023 - I am writing today hours after completing my first sprint distance triathlon. I want to use this opportunity to debrief – highlighting all the things I did well and what I’ll need to work on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s first talk about the wins. Firstly, it’s a huge accomplishment for me to finish an open water swim after the debacle at Fox Lake. There was definite fear going into it, and the only way I quelled that terror was by putting in A LOT of time in the pool and open water. During this race, I stuck to a strategy of freestyling at a manageable pace and side stroking when my breath went out of sync. I stopped once three-quarters of the way through and grabbed on to a noodle. But I am incredibly impressed by how I kept my resolve and got through to the other side, relatively unscathed. I was a bit nauseous coming out, but I was able to stabilize once I got on the bike. Another aspect of my race performance that went well was how I managed my electrolytes. I did not get dehydrated and kept pushing through the cycling and running segments.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thirdly, I loved how the logistics of this race were organized. The car rental, parking, managing the bike, packing my belongings… it was all seamless. That was the major obstacle I surpassed after Fox Lake. It displayed a lot of deliberate planning, methodical execution, and level-headedness whenever I needed to course-correct. I am also so fortunate that my tri-suit and race belt got home on time (the night before the race)! I felt more confident participating knowing that I had all the equipment necessary to succeed at this challenge.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In terms of things I’d like to work on for next time, I want to get stronger on the bike. A tune-up, in addition to spending more time practicing on the bike will be the way to go. Additionally, leg workouts targeting the quads will be helpful. I’ll aim to get some advice from Mark and any other online resources that seem credible. My swim times will definitely improve as I practice more. I’ll aim to build more endurance in the pool and open water to prepare for the 1 mile open water swim at the Chicago Triathlon. I also want to work on mobility and endurance for better running, ensuring a strong, injury-free performance during the Olympic distance event.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-desire-to-be-better&quot;&gt;The desire to be better&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had an interesting conversation after swim practice. It was regarding the process of getting better at a skill. When it comes to acquiring any skill set, there is a learning curve that can feel quite uncomfortable to cope with at times. It’s in these moments where grit and patience come in handy. It doesn’t always come down to the number of hours you’ve spent on a given activity, but if you’ve engaged in deliberate practice. Oftentimes, we engage in an activity with great enthusiasm only to find out we weren’t doing it quite right. The technique may be slightly off and we end up making the same mistakes over time, solidifying the neural structures behind that habit. These habits keep getting harder to change over time. It is for this reason that it always helps to have a coach guide you through the initial phase of learning. I have seen this quite often in my life so far.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s take swimming for example. I started in March this year, and I was far from where I needed to be to complete a triathlon. With targeted feedback from my swim coaches Monika and Steve, I have been able to correct my swimming form bit-by-bit and improve my conditioning. Being in a community of triathletes from Tuesday-Friday has also made a huge difference. It’s pushed me to give my best every single day. Today I swam 1,000 meters of the LSAC pool (4x10, with a 60 second break after every 4 lengths). It was quite challenging, especially in the later stages. But I’m really proud of myself for powering through. I felt good by the end of it. A lot of the hours I’ve put into the pool are beginning to pay off, and I’m beginning to see the fruits of my labor. There’s a lot of wisdom in working through the struggle and suffering you’re going through, getting to the other side, and looking back with incredible pride at all that you’ve accomplished. That only adds more fuel to the fire and pushes you to accomplish things you didn’t think were possible before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, let’s take strength training as an example. Having DJ as my coach and working through the early part of my fitness journey with him has made a huge difference to the way I approach lifting weights. He taught me the right form to follow and that has prevented me from suffering injuries that would have held me back. Even the injuries I faced have given me the opportunity to learn further. The whole physical therapy process has been an absolute game changer. I’ve learned so much about the way the shoulders and core engage in a coordinated fashion, helping me perform to the best of my ability. The human body is a fascinating study. It’s amazing how much we can all accomplish if we’re attuned to the mechanics of body and mind.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Third, let’s take piano as an example. Ela has been instrumental in helping me internalize the “perfect practice makes perfect” mindset. She makes sure that I’m learning all the nuggets necessary to practice correctly when I’m at home. It makes all the difference as I pick up new skills, such as finger techniques, legato, staccato, and accents. One interesting revelation I had through my piano lessons was around the different tones / accents / durations each key is held for. Each of these modulations plays a role in shaping / molding the patterns of sound and how they are perceived.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fourth, let’s talk about technology and my daily learning habits. I’ll be starting a new project beginning next week that will be closely tied to Azure and cloud computing. I’m happy to have received this opportunity, especially after all the hours that have gone into preparing for cloud certifications. I began this whole process last November (2022) and stuck with it. There were times when I felt unmotivated and wasn’t sure my efforts would pay off. This opportunity has convinced me further that I may be on the right path. I will continue to take more certifications and upskill within the cloud space. There is a time constraint I’m dealing with since the Georgia Tech semester will begin in late August. Before then, I want to pass my other 2 associate certifications (Developer and SysOps). These will be great to round out my foundational AWS knowledge, giving me the confidence to take even harder exams, adopting a multi-cloud mindset, and becoming more eloquent / knowledgeable at work with the concepts and issues I come across.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Learning how to learn, regardless of the activity. I’m beginning to enjoy the process far more. It pushes me to the limits of my capabilities, and I always come out of every such experience having discovered a new facet of myself. My days are busy, but I love every minute of it. I don’t mind the grind. This is what I want my life to look like. If I can stay true to these principles and keep progressing, I will be staying true to the purpose of my existence. I know it’s a heavy sentence, but I do believe we’re all here on this planet to walk our own path. We need to listen to this inner voice that guides us towards the road less traveled. This path will lead us towards discovering our own uniqueness that will help us actualize our own potential. This is what I believe we’re all here in this world to do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;healthy-relationships&quot;&gt;Healthy relationships&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s interesting to see which relationships are healthy and which are not. I was recently having a conversation with my father regarding this. In many interactions, he feels a bit used - as if the other person needed to get something off their chest and they were using the other person to aim their rant at. On the other hand, there are those interactions that leave both sides feeling energized. It’s a shared experience where both parties seem to benefit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I wonder what the difference is. What causes this dynamic shift? I ask this not only to seek mutually rewarding friendships, but also to be the kind of individual who does not seek to use others for his own emotional needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a Buddhist quote I heard on the Waking Up app, mentioning that “the ultimate form of generosity is non-attachment”. I keep thinking about it every now and then, and I don’t think I’ve fully grasped its meaning. However, from personal experience, I have noticed that I’ve had incredibly rewarding experiences with friends and family members who I don’t feel the need to text everyday, but it’s always a pleasure when we interact. There’s something quite pure and organic about these interactions, devoid of any ulterior motive or craving.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe there might be some truth to what I wrote yesterday - it’s only when you’re completely at peace with yourself can you seek a rewarding relationship. I think there is truth to that. If you truly enjoy your own company, you will only seek relationships that make you feel the same way. It sounds liberating - you never have to crave the other person’s presence or approval, and you’re not afraid to be your authentic self. The recipient will notice this sense of inner calm within you. They will begin to see that you’re only spending time with them because you truly enjoy their company - and for no other reason. You’re perfectly willing to walk away if you don’t feel that way anymore.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This, to me, resembles signs of a truly secure individual. It doesn’t just apply to relationships, but also towards external validation. If you’ve found peace within yourself, you would seldom need to chase that feeling outside of yourself. You’re content to put in the work for the sole reward that it offers. The work becomes the win, and you’re happy to keep doing the thing no matter what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lastly, I would like to apply this same principle towards my relationships, building genuine connections, staying grounded in the present, and enjoying each other’s company – optimizing for the process, not the result.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationships that were once a primary part of my life, i.e, my family - are no longer the same as they were. I would say that’s true in terms of my friendships as well. We change as people, our priorities shift, and we choose to spend our time in ways that do not align with how others wish to live. That seems like a healthy journey everyone must go through. I find it hard to relate to people who were once a closely-knit part of my life. Something doesn’t feel quite right anymore. When in their company, I always feel this longing to get back to work, my routine, do the things I find joy and meaning in. I suppose I’m writing this because I feel a tinge of guilt around not spending time with family, and not visiting them as often as they’d like.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It goes back to my mom calling me selfish in July 2022 when I did not wish to spend too much time around the house, idling around / hanging out. Life is short. We’re never getting this life back. Time is running out. We’re not doing ourselves any favors by living for others, remaining enslaved to their whims and desires. It’s really important to listen to one’s heart and go after the vision you’ve set for yourself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been multiple occasions in my life where I have felt less than, harboring a victim’s mindset that hasn’t done me any good. I want to do things differently this time. I am my own obstacle and only I can get in my way. I have a unique opportunity today, living in the most prosperous country in the world, having graduated from an elite university, working in a prestigious job, training for triathlons, and about to pursue a graduate degree at Georgia Tech. None of this has come easy. And it’s all actualized for me in large part due to the hard work and focus I’ve put in. I’m not relenting, ever. I owe it to myself to become the best version of myself. This time, there will be nothing that gets in my way. Because, unlike previous occasions, I’ve built the mental fortitude, physical foundation, and acquired enough financial resources to drive towards the goals I’ve always wanted to achieve. Nobody understands me like I do, and I know the deep burning desires I have for my life. If people misunderstand me, disapprove of my path, get jealous, say hurtful things… Quite frankly, that’s their problem. Because unlike previous occasions, there’s nothing they can do that can stop me from getting after my goals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;solitude--loneliness&quot;&gt;Solitude ≠ Loneliness&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Is it possible to be in solitude and not feel any sense of loneliness? This is a thought I’ve been grappling with for a while, and I’m really interested in exploring it further. A lot of the times I’ve seen people spending time with each other, even though they are not very fond of them. I think this is likely because they can’t bear to be by themselves. Shouldn’t we work on being better friends to ourselves? If we can’t bear alone time, there must be some internal dissonance we’re fleeing from. We’re distracting ourselves with external stimuli - be it mindless scrolling, TV, drugs, or alcohol.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been times in the past where I have disliked being devoid of any company. I think the primary reason for this is I was lost in thought. Patterns of thought that were destructive and self-defeating. I have found meditation and exercise to be powerful activities to escape these vicious traps. One of the primary reflections from meditating is how anything that emerges in consciousness eventually passes away. The same applies to negative experiences as well. Instead of fighting the feeling, I try to accept it wholeheartedly as another appearance within conscious experience. By not fighting it, it eventually loses its power and I’m back to feeling the same sense of calm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Speaking of calm, exercise has played a great role in reducing my anxiety and lifting my mood. It has also embedded within me the value of discipline, and how small efforts daily can compound into huge returns in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to being in solitude, I believe you can only truly enjoy another’s company if you’re totally fine with being by yourself. When I reach this state of equanimity, I only engage with individuals who I have much to learn from and with whom I can have a truly positive experience. The feeling has to be mutual. Organic relationships like these only work if both parties stand to gain from the interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over this next week, I will largely be by myself. I plan to use this time mindfully - observing myself, my tendencies, habits, thoughts - and also get some much-needed focus time to earn the rare and valuable skills that will pay great dividends in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;lifelong-learning&quot;&gt;Lifelong learning&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thought I’ve been sitting with is the importance of constant learning in our careers. The practice was easier in school with all the externalities driving us towards meeting our deadlines. It’s a bit different in the workplace. Unless you make an intentional effort to keep learning and upskilling, there is inevitably going to be a time when you feel jaded, left behind, and hopeless. You begin to doubt yourself and the innate abilities that helped you get the job in the first place. That is why I have begun to take more initiative with pursuing certifications and updating my skills outside of the projects I am currently working on at EY. An area that has piqued my curiosity is the topic of cloud computing. I am fascinated by how simple systems are able to interlink to create these complex platforms that businesses are able to run their operations on. Over this past decade, there has been a seismic shift from the traditional data center model to the cloud. I have enjoyed learning about the fundamentals. Since November of last year, I have passed the beginner level exams prepared by AWS, Azure and Google Cloud. A month back, I also passed the FinOps certified practitioner examination. With this shift to the cloud, companies have to rethink their finances and how they should appropriately budget their IT spend. Cloud follows a variable expense model, and, without the appropriate guardrails in place, there is a high likelihood of significant cost overruns. This disincentivizes organizations from transforming and can stifle the pace of innovation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope to keep investing my time and attention towards upskilling in this space. I am setting time 2 weeks from now to take the AWS Solutions Architect Associate examination. It is comparatively more challenging than the exams I have previously sat through, but I am confident that I have the intelligence, fortitude and work ethic to see this through.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Two other topics that interest me are AI and DevOps. In order to learn more about these topics, I enrolled in the computer science program at Georgia Tech, which I will be beginning in August. I’ll be specializing in machine learning, which will expose me to courses that will broaden my understanding of the field. Additionally, to learn more about DevOps, I hope to eventually progress and pass the AWS DevOps Specialty examination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Credentials are nice to have, but not sufficient. At a certain point, I need to stop with the tunnel vision of attaining “x” number of certifications and getting As in all my classes. Even looking back at my undergraduate career, a lot of these objectives feel quite meaningless. What’s truly valuable is the quality learning time I’m engaging in every day. It’s an opportunity to grow as an individual, build my curiosities, and look with awe at all the amazing things happening in the world. Our experiences in life are determined through the perspective we see them through. I believe the mindset I bring towards my life and all the things I do is what will ultimately matter in the end. Any successes/failures that emerge from them are only illusions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an age as dynamic as this, the ability to learn and reinvent oneself is of paramount importance. I have committed myself to the learning process and have already begun reaping the benefits. No matter how hard it gets with the current project I’m on, I will dedicate time everyday to prepare for my certification exams. Additionally, I am incredibly fortunate to have received the opportunity to study computer science at Georgia Tech - one of the top technical universities in the world. The coursework will keep my brain sharp and make my mind rigorous and flexible as it engages with complex topics. It will be challenging to balance my time across all these activities, but it will be well worth the effort.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I’m beginning to realize, however, is learning at a consistent rate requires focus, the ability to say no, and the importance of doing less - in other words, what’s absolutely essential. The moment the Georgia Tech semester began, there was this urge within me to keep up with AWS prep, tackling the Developer certification as well. I soon came to realize this wouldn’t be productive. I only have 16 hours in a day. Within that time, I have learning, reading, meditating, fitness, and the piano to take care of. It’s best to deal with each of these activities one at a time, devoting my full attention to it before moving on to the next thing on the list. For example, with fitness, it would be very tempting to keep up with triathlon training even though we’re done with the season. That would give me more time to improve. However, that would take my attention away from CrossFit, and building strength. There is an opportunity cost no matter which activity you pick. In moments like this, you have to decide and stay consistent with the resolution. If you try to do both things, you may end up half-assing both tasks and get nowhere. Additionally, the heavy time commitment would bleed into other aspects of your life, preventing you from excelling at the other activities on your plate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also realize the value of the classes offered at Tech, and the need to make it my utmost priority. The AI courses, in particular, dovetail with the direction I want to take my life. I can picture myself working at a cutting-edge AI research organization. To get there, I am aware of the work I’ll be required to put in. But it’s not something I will shy away from. We’re all put on this Earth for a very short period of time, and it’s our sole responsibility that we reach our physical, mental, and spiritual potential. I don’t want to be on my deathbed, wishing I did more. Or wondering what my life would be like had I put in just a little more effort. I choose to live with no regrets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The universe has conspired to bring me to America, discover fitness, land a well-paying job, offer me the flexibility of work-from-home, land me a spot in a stellar CS graduate program, and give me enough free time to work on topics I truly care about. Everything in this world has been designed perfectly. Whatever that has happened in the past has occurred for a reason. It was necessary to mold me into the individual I am today, who is always learning and growing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-importance-of-showing-up&quot;&gt;The importance of showing up&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An aspect of my life that I’ve made a concerted effort to change in my ability to stay disciplined towards executing the tasks I’ve set for myself. In an effort to do so - in January of this year, I began logging my daily habits in an app called ‘Habit’. I’ve been focusing on working out, reading, learning (tech), meditating, playing the piano, and abstaining from watching TV - a massive time drain.
What I have started to notice is that (a) I have the ability to stay disciplined and hit my targets. On average, I have been completing ~84% of my habits in any given month. I have objective data to prove I am doing the things that lead me towards the life I have envisioned for myself. (b) It has demonstrated to me the power of showing up daily. After working out consistently since May 2021, my body absolutely transformed. Even personality-wise, I am not the person I was before, and this has even been pointed out by my peers. Ever since I began training for triathlons in March 2023, I have truly impressed myself by my ability to wake up at 4:45 AM from Tuesday-Friday, consistently showing up for training. I have realized the importance of repetition and consistency with playing the piano and meditating. The former has led me to improve my skills since I began in July 2022. Meditation has been an absolute game changer for me as well. I would highly recommend Sam Harris’ ‘Waking Up’ app. His daily 20 minute meditation has made me less distracted by the spiraling effects of my own thought patterns and remain more firmly grounded in the present moment. (c) Having more discipline has removed the uncertainty and a majority of the day-to-day anxiety in my life. I wake up each day with a clear mission in my mind, and I know who I am trying to become in the process. I have a clear vision for becoming the individual I was always meant to be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me get something straight. Friction is an inevitable part of much of what I do. There were times during open water season, where swimming was the last thing I wanted to do. Getting up early in the morning is one thing, convincing myself that I won’t drown is another (I’m not a great swimmer). I would bring my safety buoy just in case and simply shut off that part of my brain that doesn’t want me to go that extra mile.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Same thing applies to writing. It’s difficult to write in my journal in the morning, first thing when I wake up. I have my moments when the last thing I’d like to do is to get out of my bed and write in my journal. I try to console myself by saying – “hey, at least I’m writing something everyday”, and that’s true. I just hope I don’t lose this habit due to inconsistent cues. The location (my desk) and the reward (day chaining) remain the same. However, with a consistent cue, the habit stays solid and there’s a high chance it gets done regularly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I push my body quite a lot as part of triathlon training. Injury is always a reality I have to deal with. Different parts of my body kept harassing me at different times. My left foot, my right IT hand, my left shoulder, my lower back… the list goes on. I have learned to accept it. Yes, there will be struggle involved but proactively dealing with it, engaging in adequate physical therapy, stretches, following proper running form, doing strength training, as well as getting adequate rest will be the catalyst towards recovery and future growth. There’s a similar resistance I face while trying to study. It’s much harder to prepare for certifications now that I’m staffed on a full-time project. By the looks of it, the project I’m about to start is not going to be easy. I can already foresee long hours and the team requiring me to carry my weight. I have to confess though that it is only through certification preparation and the knowledge gained during that time that I was able to land the project I’m currently on. I don’t want to give up on the thing that landed me this early bout of success.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It’s important to stay realistic and understand that I only have so much time in a day. Even if it’s 30 minutes - 1 hour of prep work, I still want to keep showing up and maintain the habit. Life happens and we sometimes will need to prioritize other areas, but that is exactly the time that maintaining the habit becomes that much more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Life is suffering. I will face trials and tribulations every single day. However, it is my response to these situations that will ultimately define my success/failure in life. I must never complain or feel sorry for myself. As long as I’m breathing, there is an opportunity to go out and get after it.
It’s easy to make excuses and justify taking it easy because … oh, you’re already doing so much. But as Rich Roll’s book says, excuses are just that. Excuses. I will take full responsibility.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are days I feel lost. There are times when I’m unsure where my life is headed. There are moments when I wonder whether I made the right decision to come to the United States. It happens every so often, but it’s also when I need to remind myself of the growth I’ve seen as an individual these past 5 years.
I’ve physically transformed, got a job offer from a prestigious company, completed a 4 triathlons, learned to play the piano at an intermediate level, invested in my mental health through meditation and journaling, passed several cloud certifications, received an opportunity to work on a cloud engagement, which - as a staff - is uncommon. I have many things to be proud of. Coming into this country in August 2018, starting off from scratch, and in 5 years - today, as we enter August 2023 - I have made incredible strides. I am super proud of myself. Bad days are there. There will be times when I feel low. That’s totally normal. It’s okay to feel like that. Just know you have many things to be grateful for and there are adventures on the horizon that are waiting to be unraveled.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I still remember the day when someone asked me why I decided to train for a triathlon. A great answer popped in my head this evening: “To see myself achieve things I didn’t think I was capable of.” Our mind has this tendency to chronically undersell our abilities to ourselves. We always settle for mediocrity when it’s convenient. If I worried about my thoughts and feelings before going to workout, I would never have been able to achieve the body transformations that I did over the past 2+ years. I was listening to Huberman talk about how Goggins is the perfect embodiment of the phrase: “Mood follows action.” That’s a great mantra to keep in mind. Our daily habits and behaviors are what ultimately define our success. Even if we didn’t “feel” like going that extra mile, simply silencing that naysaying voice and going ahead can make all the difference. By achieving hard tasks, my life is imbued with a deeper sense of purpose. I feel connected to the path I’m on and the life I’m shaping for myself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that triathlon season is over, I’d like to keep up with my workouts. It feels tempting to not push as intensely as I did between March and August. That was the exact reason why I signed up for CrossFit. I hope to stay consistent with the activity, making it to at least 4 sessions in a week. I will responsibly manage my diet, sleep and general health to perform in my classes. I also don’t want to lose the progress I made as a swimmer this year. I wish to get back to taking swim lessons and staying in shape as March 2024 rolls around.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;on-journaling-itself&quot;&gt;On journaling itself&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Context&lt;/em&gt;: &amp;lt;&amp;gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I started a practice in late July 2023 of daily morning pages. Each day, I aim to write about 2 pages of whatever comes to my mind. In the process, I am learning to articulate my thoughts clearly and have the logic hold up when re-read. I got this idea from Tim Ferriss on his YouTube channel, where he spoke about the importance of writing and its potential to impact just about every aspect of one’s life. I have always wanted to improve my ability to write, cogently express my thoughts about a particular topic, and share it with my readers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through practice and repetition, I can attest to how helpful this journaling habit is to me. There were many negative patterns of thought that I felt consumed by, but this most certainly helped me feel better. And not in a wrap-a-band-aid-on-it kind of way, but in a deeply therapeutic way. Freezing my thoughts into words on paper / a screen and rationalizing through every intricacy has helped me gain a lot of clarity. Otherwise, it’s really hard to arrive at these conclusions by having thoughts simmer in your head. Articulation is an integral step.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This applies even to goal-setting. In an attempt to land a project in my consulting job, I mapped out my networking strategy on 7/15 in my journal. The next day, I executed this plan to the tee. Lo and behold, things worked out. I’ll be starting a new project beginning next week that will be closely tied to Azure and cloud computing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I recently had this desire to share my work through a blog. I’ve mostly set up the web infrastructure piece of it, using Jekyll and AWS. All of my writings have been categorized into their respective themes. Writing has helped me understand myself better and clarified the direction I’d like to take my life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I’m creating this blog for myself. I won’t mind if nobody ever looks at it. That’s fine. What matters is the soul with which I put my work out. How the world perceives it is the world’s problem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;closing-thoughts&quot;&gt;Closing Thoughts&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congratulate the reader on making it this far. End however you like.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name></name></author><category term="journaling" /><category term="routine" /><category term="mental-health" /><summary type="html">A ritual that has aided my mental health in a profound way</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/pics/morning-pages.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/pics/morning-pages.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>